[Music]
hi there
my name is Andrew Sweeney I'm a blogger
a writer a teacher a musician sometimes
I put out YouTube videos I've recently
done a series of conversations with a
guy named Alexander bard and I'm about
to launch a new set of conversations
with him but this video is about jiseok
and Peterson and the recent debate I'm
an admirer of both men for different
reasons last year I wrote a short piece
where I defended Peterson again against
she checks rather shallow critique
however over time I've also been
developing a critique of Peterson and I
have renewed interest in jiseok so I
started binging on Gees exFAT philosophy
books around the time of the Trump
election the last book I read of his was
called total recoil and also read living
in the end times I liked his titles very
much anyway shortly after - or journey
into Dziedzic the Peterson revolution
hit and I spend a great deal of time
thinking and writing about the dangerous
[Music]
professor from Canada all right and
they're both very different so I'm going
to talk about some of the differences
and similarities
so these xboxone are a jungle well you
need a machete to cut through them
there's a lot of dense
lakhani and verbiage verbiage but also
great insights
Zizek is a good storyteller a real
humorist which sometimes makes people
forget that he's also a important
Hegelian philosopher and Peter since
politics often get in the way of his
deeper works so this has been one of my
concerns
with Peterson is too let's get to the
heart of Peterson and sort of try to
ignore most of the the politics let's
start with the end of the debate I'm
gonna go backwards here and the
concluding remarks so Peterson ended on
a quite an optimistic note he said he
was hoping that he would that people
would leave the debate with a belief in
the power of communication between
people of different views
Ziza on the other hand was much less
rosy he hoped to shatter people a bit
one to stir the pot so both men have a
professed pessimism
although Peterson is less pessimistic
and the fact that Jesus is a
philosophical pessimist makes him a
strange kind of Marxist which Peterson
pointed out in the debate since Marxism
is often about creating a utopian future
another thing which is interesting to
note and I've written about this before
is the physical energetic differences
between the two men some people might
think that body language isn't a
relevant subject but how we present
herself might have something to do with
our philosophy might be may be related
so Z Zack has the body language of a
kind of a gesture the fool the idiot
he's always twitching and sniffing and
just sticky leading him sometimes going
into this fetal position he's sort of
like a character actor he uses his
bodily tics for you know comedic
rhetorical purposes the point is that
the clown can say more than the ordinary
person can say because he is an outsider
and Peterson's persona is strikingly
different he's the Protestant preacher
the gentleman
the person can very concern was saying
just the right word
he never stutters so you have zis Act
the court jester and Peterson though the
old-fashioned preacher somewhat which is
a nice dynamic so Peterson is very still
and poised he's he's elegant he's clear
whereas he's Equis mannequin he was he
has a sort of trademarks accent and
stuttering and I was thinking that this
is like order meeting chaos Peterson's
all about order jisuk is all about chaos
on some level which isn't to say that
Ziza is not capable of being orderly but
he likes to be provocative and say odd
strange things rather than keep to the
script in fact he was never on the
script during this debate and I also was
thinking that beneath Peterson's very
cool not cool very proper demeanor
there's some shadowy elements so in my
first piece about Peterson and Susak I
wrote about the communication
differences between the two men I said
that Peterson is a good listener
music doesn't listen he monologues but I
like the fact that Z Zach doesn't put on
airs or pretend to lower himself to the
the usual you know bullshit whereas
Peterson on the other hand is very
magnanimous always very available to the
audience as a clinical psychologist he
makes an effort to listen and perhaps
this is the secret to his power as a
healer and even a priest of sorts you
heal people by listening to their
stories which is what
psychoanalysis is about more or less but
his basic argument is that by
strengthening the individual you
strengthen the community which
strengthens the world clean your room
these that made the point however that
you know you could also tell the North
Korean to to clean his room and be very
orderly and treat his family well and be
a nice kind of docile system but there's
obviously something more to the human
spirit than that but Peterson is quite
right to say that in order to really
help the world we have to deal with
what's intimate what's near the too much
social justice activity all this social
justice stuff is lacking a certain
hard-nosed pragmatism and intelligence
of wisdom of depth that it's very
important to develop our character and
all that so what I'm gonna argue here
however is that this is limited that the
individualistic philosophy is a lonely
Street it has its particular limits and
also it's an ideology so zis exposition
is that everything is an ideology you
know he gave the example of German
toilets they're an expression of German
ideology and then this just is to tell
us how very deep ideology goes so
perhaps Peterson's anti ideology is
actually the ideology of liberalism and
individualism I think it sees like has a
point here you have to constantly refine
and create ideology an ideology means
literally just the science of ideas so
there's ideological possession and maybe
there's a conscious way of creating
ideology but it turned out that ideology
is usually work used in a very negative
sense well in my first piece I was a bit
unfair towards eASIC I called him a
postmodernist but he's
so very critical of this lack of a grand
narrative and post-modernism the sort of
idealization of the marginal person and
all that and some people have been
calling jejak just like they called
peterson Eurocentric zis ik is very much
into theory you could say he thinks
theory is very important Peterson is
very into pragmatism so you could say
that Jesus is more let's say a
philosopher a pure philosopher and
Peterson is more like a hands-on
psychologist you know in the school of
Jung and Freud and all that
he's his concern is changing people
directly in a very direct way so so in a
way that this is one of the reasons
Peterson makes people so upset is that
like he like you made people very upset
is that he's so pragmatic and so
straightforward that DIAC it drives the
academics crazy because their academics
right so on one hand we have Peterson
emphasizing the individual and on the
other hand we have Dziedzic emphasizing
no social bureaucracy and collectivism
so this brings me to my friend and
co-conspirator Alexander bard
was clearly articulated this and he's
helping me make a somewhat of a friendly
critique of both men in bards book the
netic rats which is a great book by the
way he speaks of trends and counter
trends so counter trends are sort of
what the fallback position when you
don't have a vision to the future the
counter trend here might be nationalism
or traditionalism you know in the face
of the trend of globalism so the world
is becoming more and more global so
people become more and more reactionary
so this is perhaps why Peterson is so
conservative he's falling back into
let's say Western individualism and
maybe a Cold War sort of Red Scare
rhetoric which doesn't mean that he
hasn't beautifully and correctly
described the dynamics of
totalitarianism only his remedy might be
not complete so collectivists and
individualists pathologies will
certainly arise in the future but they
won't be the same in the internet age we
need some other kind of diagnosis so
interestingly Bart considers himself not
a socialist or a liberal not a
collectivist or an individualist but
rather a communist which is this
heretical word especially to Peterson
and his gang and I'd rather say
communalist but for him it's all about
reintegrating the tribal communal life
and the fact that tribalism is so deep
inside of us you know and we need a
healthy version of the tribe of the
commune so perhaps the question of
happiness or rather deep meaning and
fulfillment it's not about the
individual it's about finding one's
place of maximum meaning in a community
and Bart makes the point and this is
somewhat of a Buddhist point as well
that there is no such thing as an
isolated atomic individual per se most
of the deeper spiritual traditions
arrive at this point as well we're
social beings we have communal needs and
we don't exist apart from that so again
it's not the Petersons would deny this
only it's not emphasized in his thought
also on
to capitalism erich fromm who was one of
the frankfurt school people he wrote a
book called to have her to be so in the
capitalist society it's all about having
where's the meaningful existence we
search for we look for resides in being
so yes it's important to develop the
individual but it's being in the team
that we thrive so you can only be happy
and even if this is a rather lame idea
just you know the purpose of life to be
happy is all the existentialist point
out it's not a goal in itself but
well-being etc is is maybe only possible
in the larger family the larger tribe
and this is the critique of this
individualism we're making here so
Nietzsche might be the the champion of
19th century individualism just as Marx
was the champion of 19th century
collectivism but Nietzsche ended up
alone and we all know where what happens
when society becomes too collectivist
Peterson has spoken about that in length
but the problem is according to bard
that neither of these two people have a
vision of the future or a revolutionary
theory that's why they both tend towards
conservatism gzx defense of social
democracy and a controlled free market
mechanism it's not revolutionary and
Peterson's conservatism isn't that
radical form of conservatism so Peterson
is a moderate conservative and Dziedzic
is a moderate leftist the politics are
the least interesting part of these two
men's thinking as I've already said so
if you want to really get behind you
know Peterson and Dziedzic you need to
know where they come from who their
masters were who they study
so it's G Zack its Hagel on Lacan you
know both very interesting characters
and for Peterson its Nietzsche and yo so
if you want to know about their
worldviews you know read Hegel and Lacan
and Nietzsche and yo so why are these
men important despite the critiques we
might have they are the people's
philosophers the people have elected
them so to speak they're popular not
through votes or book marketing or any
of that it's all you know their massive
popularity is all word of mouth which
means that they're responding to
something that's actually happening and
we need more of these popular
philosophers popular philosophers with
integrity
rather than pop philosophers so both men
have proved that there is a mass
interest in in thinking right that we
are thinking creatures we need to think
our way through these things and we
don't just want ideological cliches or
television sound bites there's a hunger
for thought and both men show that that
the the subculture is it's become bigger
than the dominant culture in a sense
YouTube has become bigger than TV
Digital has become bigger than broadcast
and digital is a two-way conversation
right broadcast is just a one-way
conversation so this is interesting
creative chaotic times and
the Atheist puts it the Holy Spirit is
arising so without being too religious
let's just say that the Holy Spirit is
generative intelligence its intelligence
it's bright intelligence which is
transforming of people it's beyond
Instagram it's beyond marketing it's
beyond effects
it's beyond well there's a philosopher
called Harry Frankfurt and calls it
bullshit it's beyond bullshit
so these akin Peterson are very great
anti bullshit personalities I think and
even if they differ in their analysis of
what the bullshit is they've brought a
new authenticity to the conversation so
contrary to what Peterson people often
say about Peterson he's a he's a
self-help guru and all that I would say
that I'd say that he's tapping into
something much deeper I'd say he's more
of a priest or a faith healer he's
helping thousands of people get their
lives together he's making us he's
making young spoiled millennial punks
you know want to become adults he's
promoting what Alexander bard calls them
this is a nice term adult offical we
need to become adults you need to offer
addled remedies to the world rather than
just engage in armchair activism and
various social justice Tantrums there's
just too many babies in that and the
revolutionary movements they're immature
they haven't dealt with their own
traumatism they may be doing more harm
than good so we need to be as Peterson
and G's Eck are critical of these victim
and cults critical of the alt right or
alt left hysteria but sympathetic to
real social injustice is obviously so
what about their writing
um I think zzg check excuse me Alice its
Dziedzic I think Dziedzic is a better
writer he has more sort of flow in
spontaneity in this writing
he writes faster and that's not to say
that Peterson isn't a good writer he's
just very compressed and perfectionistic
so it's his first book last meeting it
is a tough read he he writes and
rewrites every sentence hundreds of
times which makes it very dense and hard
to penetrate
whereas jejak is very prolific and he's
I guess he's more free in his expression
I don't want to critique twelvers for
life but it's it's a peripheral book
it's not a important book whereas I
think master meanings is an important
book I think twelvers rules for life was
perhaps written too hastily for the
publisher even if it is a great you know
popular self health manual you can get
all that from Peterson's lectures and
everything is in maps and meaning maps
in meaning his was written in blood
so Nicci's phrase so even if it's
imperfect it has it has the essence of
Peterson in it so it's I think it's an
important book so hopefully Peterson
will write another major book but I
think maybe he put everything that one
book it's not a criticism and I think
that he's also
embodying this Guttenberg revolution
that he talks about where the spoken
word matters so back to the debate this
debate was never about happiness or
liberalism versus Marxism and I've been
thinking that that's because that debate
is old old hat classic liberalism and
Orthodox Marxism are not important
except as historical systems we need new
imaginative vocabulary for the social
and economic dynamics today
and I'm with my friend Alexander Bart on
this that we have to come up with a new
grand narrative and we can use marks we
can reinvent him without becoming insane
collectivists and there's a new sort of
dynamic and class struggle between what
he calls the netic rats and the consume
arias the hidden people behind the
internet and the people who just consume
so that all that's to say that the rules
of the game had have shifted so in the
debate both men agree that liberalism
won the war of the 20th century one that
ideological war but the question then
remains is has the dynamic now shifted
are we in the age of eminent ecological
collapse do we have to think of
development in a different way do we
have to rethink communalism or communism
you know of some sort and living
together in a different way and in order
to be Christian you're part of a
congregation you're part of a you go to
church just like if you're a Buddhist
here you're part of the Buddhist Sangha
you know you go and gather together it's
not a lonely individualist enterprise so
if you were talking about Buddhist lingo
which I'm particularly familiar with you
could say Peterson gets the idea of
Buddha and Dharma but not the idea of
Sangha and the nuclear family is not
it's not the human unit it's a very new
organizational mode and it has its
faults pathologies and I think today
we're searching for different ways of
being together and we need a
congregation we need a song I forgot to
talk about religion you can't talk about
religion without talking about
life so eight billion sovereign
individuals is a pretty lost world so
anyway what I'm arguing here is that a
Peterson perhaps is too much of an
apologist for individualism and Zedek
perhaps is too much of an apologist
apologist for collectivism the point is
both men don't have a grand narrative
and what is the grand narrative and what
they should the grand narrative be we
are creating narratives we're creating
grand narratives all the time and and
one of the grand narratives we're
creating is a sort of doomsday fatalism
related to ecology and a kind of zombie
consumerist nihilism and you know
there's all kinds of narratives social
you know collective narratives being
created and perhaps we need something
higher to aim at in the 21st century
which is very different than the 20th
century and we can't use 19th century
modes and expect them to work in the in
the 21st century you know whether it's
classical market Marxism or free-market
liberalism there's no invisible hand
there's no perfect communist state but
we need to perhaps need a need a utopian
vision of a better world you know a
promised land bard thinks this should be
called the echo topia but who knows what
we will call it car Marx
it was badly treated by Peterson he
didn't he didn't show a great knowledge
of Marx and if you're arguing against
Marx perhaps you need to you need to
study him a bit more deeply and not just
the people who hate him and we could
also say that is Marx and you know
Peterson adores Nietzsche Ameche
inspired Hitler to a great degree does
that mean that Nietzsche is the devil
so if Marx inspired Stalinism does that
mean Marx as the devil I don't know
maybe Hitler misread Nietzsche and maybe
Mao and Stalin misread Marx so what with
Marx maybe we have to separate the wheat
from the chaff to use Peterson's
favorite expression maybe we have to
read these thinkers properly rather than
just straw Manning them in a polemical
way so Peterson is masterful at showing
the pathological elements of
post-modernism and the worst parts of
Marxism but he's Manichaean right here
he won't grant much truth value he says
he'll give the devil his due
but he's still saying the devil is still
saying it's the devil right so it seems
to be a very manichaean argument of
absolute good versus absolute evil
rather than a view beyond good and evil
right which is based more on on
pragmatism which is based on ethics
maybe Marx also saw a few things like he
actually saw communal societies
developing in England in Germany he
definitely didn't promote revolution in
feudal states like China and Russia in
the 19th century so then the question so
the question becomes you know also why
you know what about the negative aspects
of capitalism like mass alienation and
depression and
all these different psychosis is that
the you know the system of late
capitalism engenders so Peterson doesn't
have this critique of linked capitalism
and its predatory kind of economics and
all the environmental rapaciousness you
know he hasn't been able to show that
this risk economy as may be running out
of steam so what kind of system do we
need
well nonzero-sum game non-rival
cooperative economics you know animated
by a grand narrative one thing is for
sure we don't need bloody revolution and
we don't need post-modernism postmodern
relativism and yes we needed values
decades of values and yes there's
something above and below us unlike what
John Lennon said so we need to look up
to somebody in something and we need to
understand that we're part of you know a
larger story oh I'm with Peterson on
that Peterson also admits that there are
unjust hierarchies so we could say that
maybe the movement in history towards
egalitarianism and
is a good thing and Petersen doesn't
have this particular gala terrine of his
vision
even if he's totally correct to say that
equality of opportunity is what we
should be aiming at and not equality of
outcome I had another thought which is
provocative and I thought is who's the
revolutionary here who was the
hot-headed revolutionary is a Dziedzic
or Peterson again perhaps Peterson's
hatred of marks indicate indicates this
sort of intimacy with Marxist ideas
perhaps he comes from the left and he's
reacting against Marx but he's got some
left is you know qualities him
so he's the he's the leader of the
revolutionary of the proletariat so to
speak
lifting up working-class men everywhere
and jejak on the other hand is an
elitist you know he's a burgeois elitist
and he's a bit of a conservative he's
critical of progressive movements even
while he supports them and he's an
apologist for Christianity which he uses
the greatest moral system of all time
which is not exactly what you would
think your average Marxist revolutionary
who thinks that religion is the opiate
of PEEP of the people what would think
Peterson wants to change the world he's
out to change the world one person at a
time I don't know if I could make a
sustained argument the Peterson as a
Marxist and Susak is a conservative but
as a thought experiment and provocation
maybe it works a little bit the point is
there's this shadowy negation of each
affirmation of a belief this is maybe
this is what Lacan is about I'm not sure
I don't know certainly it's what Carl
Jung and the shadow is about so the idea
is that the part of yourself that you've
rejected that you despise that you hate
may be animating you to a certain extent
and so then maybe music is a closeted
conservative and Peterson is a closeted
Marxist in any case I love both these
men I think they embodied the spirit of
the time I think they're very honest and
they're not beholden to media companies
which is so refreshing and Peterson is
honest enough to talk about virtue and
character and all the old-fashioned
values and Dziedzic is honest enough to
confess his perversions and be
unpolitical e correct and both are
attacking this shallow moralizing
which is great so a good thinker has to
be offensive to Dogma and ruffle
feathers you know jejak ruffles Noam
Chomsky's feathers which makes me think
Noam Chomsky is a bit of a Puritan
at Peterson is you know offensive to a
lot of people on the left and the right
you know the church people love him and
hate him the social justice warriors to
him he some sort of you know bad daddy
I think they have daddy issues but
there's people on the Left who are
probably closet Peter Sohn Ian's like me
but I haven't been in the closet I've
just been saying so again hallelujah
these men are out there we need these
fights and Wars of intellect not of
actual worse the more more people talk
the more oh we can create a reasonable
Society and it's great that these events
are big like sporting events you know
it's raising the level of the culture
and I think both men have this great
sense of humor especially Dziedzic and
we need to have a sense of humor above
all we need to flirt and joke and you
know sometimes talk dirty and not fear
this intense social castration that is
everywhere you know these days we have
to be humorous but deadly humorous and
deadly serious at the same time so you
know I could take these people these men
they're both flawed Peterson Peterson's
individuality is a flawed philosophy
these are collectivism and pessimism
it's lacking something what I think is
missing is it's the right idea of
community of the Commons of the Buddhist
Sangha of the congregation small sacred
communities a remedy to too much
individualism we all know the costs are
too much collectivism which is even
worse
because it just destroys everything
right so I think we need small Tsongas
to cultivate the holy spirit
that's where intelligence blossoms and
that's where even the the saint because
Peterson's kind of like has a saintly
quality and the pervert Dziedzic has
this perverted quality you know they're
both allowed to be there they're both
welcome hallelujah and thanks for
listening